A Calendar of The Jefferson Papers of the University of Virginia
Special Collections, University of Virginia Library
- Series I: Dated Materials
  - THOMAS JEFFERSON, Monticello, to JAMES MADISON., 1823 February 16.; LS. 1 pp. #3707. Clifton Waller Barrett Library.
    Legislature empowered Literary Board to supply more funds to University. Mr. Cabell and Mr. Loyall approved acceptance of loans; if Madison approves, T. J. and John Hartwell Cocke can proceed to employ workmen without meeting of Board of Visitors.
    [3019]
  - JAMES MADISON to THOMAS JEFFERSON., 1823 February 19.; ALS. 1 pp. #6455.
    Congratulations on loan for the University. Suggests that work begin without formal meeting of the Board of Visitors.
    [3020]
  - JAMES MADISON to THOMAS JEFFERSON, Monticello., [1823 February 19].; ALS. 1 pp. Tracing, from original in "Livingston Collection." #38-755. Originally incorrectly dated [1820].
    [1831]
  - THOMAS JEFFERSON, Monticello, to JOHN HARTWELL COCKE, Bremo., 1823 February 21.; ALS. 1 pp. Endorsed by T. J. Cocke Papers, #3184.
    Requests his attendance to discuss the hiring of workmen for the Rotunda, since legislature has permitted a $60,000 loan. Expects written authorization from James Breckenridge, Joseph Cabell, George Loyall, and James Madison. Mentions Arthur Brockenbrough, James Dinsmore, and John Neilson.
    [1978]
  - MARTHA JEFFERSON, Spring Grove, Lunenberg County, to THOMAS JEFFERSON, Monticello., 1823 February 25.; ALS. 4 pp. Endorsed by T. J. Carr-Cary Papers, #1231.
    Requesting her cousin's aid in settling the affairs of her deceased brother, George Jefferson. Believes that John Garland Jefferson and Patrick Gibson are being unfair to her.
    [1979]
  - JOSEPH CARRINGTON CABELL, Williamsburg, to THOMAS JEFFERSON, Monticello., 1823 February 26.; ALS. 2 pp. Endorsed by T. J. #2791. Printed: Cabell 277-278.
    Law regarding seats on the Board of Visitors. Contracts for the library should be for a definite amount. References to Chapman Johnson and John Augustine Smith.
    [1980]
  - THOMAS JEFFERSON UNIVERSITY OF VIRGINIA. SOUTH ELEVATION OF THE ROTUNDA WITH SOUTH ELEVATIONS OF PAVILIONS IX AND X., [1823 February]; Ink with tinted washes. Paper VW. 17 1/2 x 11 in. #2332.
    Probably drawn by John Neilson. Previously attributed to Cornelia Jefferson Randolph.
    [N-354]
  - THOMAS JEFFERSON, Monticello, to SIDNEY MORSE, New Haven., 1823 March 9.; ALS. 1 pp. Photostat. Endorsed by T. J. Original owned by B. D. Foster. #3214.
    Expressing thanks for a copy of Morse's "Geography". Age prevents his offering detailed criticism of tables, but notes omission of William and Mary from list of colleges.
    [1981]
  - THOMAS J. O'FLAHERTY, Rappahannock Academy, Caroline County, to THOMAS JEFFERSON, Monticello., 1823 March 10.; ALS. 3 pp. Endorsed by T. J. Greek, Latin, French, English. RG-1/3/3.761.
    Application for chair of languages at University of Virginia. Transmits four letters, to be returned, from Robert S. Garnett, Thomas Cooper, and himself.
    [1982]
  - ARTHUR SPICER BROCKENBROUGH, University of Virginia, to THOMAS JEFFERSON., 1823 March 11.; ALS. 2 pp. Endorsed by T. J. RG-1/3/3.811.
    Brockenbrough encloses contracts for work at the University of Virginia with [James] Dinsmore and [John] Neilson. See 1823 March 12 for contracts.
  - THOMAS JEFFERSON, Monticello, to ARTHUR SPICER BROCKENBROUGH, University., 1823 March 12.; ALS. 1 pp. RG-5/3. Endorsed by T. J. Enclosure: DS. 3 pp. Endorsed by T. J. Another copy. AL. 1 pp. File draft.
    Returns contracts (for work on the Rotunda) with James Dinsmore, John Neilson, and Thorn & Chamberlain. Requests statement of funds as work progresses. Enclosure: contracts with Dinsmore and Neilson.
    [1983]
  - THOMAS JEFFERSON, Monticello, to BOARD OF VISITORS, UNIVERSITY of VIRGINIA. Circular., 1823 March 12.; 2 items. Each: LS. 1 pp. Endorsed by T. J. Copies sent to John Hartwell Cocke ( #38-163 ) and to Joseph Carrington Cabell ( #201 ). Printed: Cabell 278-279.
    Contracts made by Arthur Spicer Brockenbrough with Thorn & Chamberlain, John Neilson, and James Dinsmore for work on the Rotunda.
    [1984]
  - THOMAS JEFFERSON to MR. HUNTINGTON., 1823 March 17.; ANS. 1 pp. Photostat. Original owned by H. I. Hutton. #4303.
    Invitation to dine at Monticello with Mr. Dodge of Marseilles.
    [3021]
  - JAMES MADISON, Montpelier, to THOMAS JEFFERSON., 1823 March 21.; ALS. 2 pp. Endorsed by T. J. #4610.
    Progress on Rotunda. Letter from Thomas J. O'Flaherty. Professor Edward Everett of Boston must seem heretic to New England.
    [3022]
  - JOSEPH CARRINGTON CABELL, Williamsburg, to THOMAS JEFFERSON, Monticello., 1823 March 24.; ALS. 3 pp. Endorsed by T. J. #2791. Printed: Cabell 280-282.
    Contracts for the library. Funds for the purchase of books and apparatus. References to John Hartwell Cocke and Chapman Johnson.
    [1985]
  - THOMAS JEFFERSON, Monticello, to THOMAS J. O'FLAHERTY, Rappahannock Academy., 1823 March 26.; ALS. 2 pp. File draft. Endorsed by T. J. RG-1/3/3.761.
    Returns papers which have been communicated to James Madison. Cannot appoint professors until University's debt is discharged. On verso: calculations (for slaves' clothing?).
    [1986]
  - THOMAS JEFFERSON, Monticello, to CREED TAYLOR, Farmville., 1823 March 27.; ALS. 1 pp. Creed Taylor Papers, #1232. Another MS. in MHi.
    Merits of the Journal of the Law School sent to T. J. by Taylor. (The law school referred to is one conducted by Taylor at his estate, Needham).
    [1987]
  - THOMAS JEFFERSON FINANCIAL STATEMENT., 1823 April 1.; AD. 2 pp. Edgehill-Randolph Papers, #1397.
    Expenses and income in Albemarle and Bedford. Plans for payment of his own debts by 1827, of Wilson C. Nicholas' by 1830, and "the lands will all be saved". List of his creditors: [Joseph] Antrim, Edmund Bacon, Bank of the United States, Bank of Virginia, Joseph Bishop, Brands' executors, Bramham & Bibb, Youen Carden, Hugh Chisholm, Dabney Cosby, Martin Dawson, Dodge & Oxnard, Francis Eppes, John Wayles Eppes, Farmer's Bank, John Gorman, Mr. Gough, Elijah Ham, [Frederick W.?] Hatch, David Higginbotham, John Jones, James Leitch, Leroy & Bayard, James Lyle, Charles Massie, B. Miller, John Neilson, Mr. Pini, Hanah Proctor, Dr. Ragland, James Rawlings, Archibald Robertson, University of Virginia, Dr. Watkins, Mr. Welsh, John Winn, and Joel Yancey.
    [1988]
  - THOMAS JEFFERSON, Monticello, to ROBERT WALSH, Philadelphia., 1823 April 5.; ALS. 1 pp. #782.
    Regrets that physical disability prevents him from providing material for Walsh's projected biography. Biography ought not to be written while the subject is alive, because of difficulty in being properly critical and because he should have access to the letters of the person while writing. "... the letters of a person... form the only full and genuine journal of his life; and few can let them go out of their own hands while they live. a life written after these hoards become opened to investigation must supercede any previous one." Correa a member of the Cortes and in poor health, disapproves of our administration.
    [1989]
  - THOMAS JEFFERSON MEMORANDUM on FINANCES of the UNIVERSITY., 1823 April 6.; AD. 1 pp. File draft. Endorsed by T. J. RG-5/3.
    Arthur Spicer Brockenbrough's and Martin Dawson's estimate of debts, subscriptions, annuity, prospects of help from legislature, and immediate loans needed for Rotunda.
    [1990]
  - ARTHUR SPICER BROCKENBROUGH to the RECTOR AND VISITORS OF THE UNIVERSITY OF VIRGINIA., 1823 April 7.; ALS. 2 pp. Endorsed by T. J. RG-1/3/3.811.
    Brockenbrough encloses contract with Mr. Coffee [not present] because Coffee is "dissatisfied and complains heavily of his bargain." Brockenbrough also asks for a public statement on his performance as Proctor since his character has been "furiously attacked by an anonymous writer under the name of a Farmer."
  - THOMAS JEFFERSON, Monticello, to JOHN ADLUM., 1823 April 11.; ALS. 1 pp. Owned by Thomas Jefferson Memorial Foundation, #3177.
    Acknowledging a gift of wine. Refuses comment on Adlum's book on wine culture.
    [1991]
  - THOMAS JEFFERSON, Monticello, to JAMES BRECKENRIDGE, Fincastle, Va., 1823 April 12.; ALS. 1 pp. Endorsed by T. J. Printed: B of R VI 47 (MS. in DLC), #38-163-a.
    Sends receipt for Chapman Johnson's subscription to the University. Hopes Breckenridge's election to the legislature will ensure remission of University's debt. Estimate of present debt.
    [1992]
  - THOMAS JEFFERSON, Monticello, to ARTHUR SPICER BROCKENBROUGH., 1823 April 22.; ALS. 1 pp. Endorsed by T. J. RG-5/3.
    Instructions for James Dinsmore and John Neilson on the entablature of the Rotunda.
    [1993]
  - GEORGE BLAETTERMANN, London, to THOMAS JEFFERSON, Monticello., 1823 April 24.; ALS. 2 pp. Endorsed by T. J. RG-1/3/3.761.
    Requests information as to when he should begin his work at the University. Has toured Germany, France, and Holland collecting materials for lectures. Wishes to know if his books may enter duty free.
    [1994]
  - THOMAS JEFFERSON, Monticello, to WILLIAM J. COFFEE., 1823 April 30.; ALS. 1 pp. File draft. Endorsed by T. J. Edgehill-Randolph Papers, #1397.
    Payment for ornaments for the University. Mix-up in shipment. Reference to Bernard Peyton.
    [1995]
  - THOMAS JEFFERSON, Monticello, to [JOHN LAVAL]., 1823 April 30.; ALS. 1 pp. #11011.
    T. J. accepts an offer for two already-published volumes in English of Bartolomé de las Casas with the subsequent volumes to be shipped later and refuses a copy of Alexander Wilson's American ornithology as too expensive. He hopes that a less expensive version without plates might be published.
  - THOMAS JEFFERSON, Monticello, to SAMUEL SMITH, Baltimore., 1823 May 3.; LS. 2 pp. Endorsed by T. J. Printed: L & B XV 430-433; Ford X 251-252; Virginia Advocate 9 July 1830; B of R VI 436 (MS. in DLC). #2686.
    Recommends tax on whiskey to discourage its consumption, but not on imported wines. Belief in support of infant industries only when they can in the future become strong. Refuses to express an opinion on the next election.
    [1996]
  - JOHN NEILSON, University, to THOMAS JEFFERSON, Monticello., 1823 May 5.; ALS. 1 pp. Endorsed by T. J. #2686.
    Problems concerning the north front of the Rotunda.
    [1997]
  - JOHN BROWN, JR., Auditor's Office, Richmond, to THOMAS JEFFERSON, Monticello., 1823 May 8.; ALS. 1 pp. Endorsed by T. J. RG-1/3/3.761.
    Literary Fund Board has authorized loan of $40,000 to the University. Regrets his delay prevented T. J.'s trip to Poplar Forest. Mentions Alexander Garrett.
    [1998]
  - THOMAS JEFFERSON CERTIFICATE., 1823 May 10.; DS. 1 pp. (multilated). RG-1/3/3.761.
    Alexander Garrett certified as Bursar of the University of Virginia.
    [1999]
  - THOMAS JEFFERSON, Monticello, to BERNARD PEYTON., 1823 May 10.; ALS. 1 pp. #6885.
    To Bedford. T. J. Randolph believes tobacco must have reached Richmond. Payments to Jacobs and Raphael. Nail rod.
    [3023]
  - THOMAS JEFFERSON to the TREASURER OF VIRGINIA., [1823 May 10?].; AD. 2 pp. RG-1/3/3.761.
    Authorizing Alexander Garrett, Bursar of the University of Virginia, to receive funds from the Literary Fund and to transact business for the Board of Visitors.
    [2000]
  - RECTOR AND VISITORS of the UNIVERSITY. BOND to the PRESIDENT and DIRECTORS of the LITERARY FUND., 1823 May 11.; D. 2 pp. Signed by T. J. File draft. Endorsed by T. J. Witnesses: Thomas J. Randolph and W. W. Southall. RG-1/3/3.761.
    Bond for $40,000. Conditions of repayment. Note at bottom: "November 21. 23. executed a bond for 5000. D. copied verbatim from this except as to sum."
    [2001]
  - CLAUDIUS F. GOJON, Hyde Park, N. Y., to THOMAS JEFFERSON, Monticello., 1823 May 12.; ALS. 1 pp. Endorsed by T. J. RG-1/3/3.761.
    Application for a position at the University of Virginia teaching French, Spanish, and Italian. Lists experiences at the University of France and at Dr. Allen's Academy. Refers him to P. S. DuPonceau.
    [2002]
  - BOARD OF VISITORS OF THE UNIVERSITY OF VIRGINIA to PRESIDENT AND DIRECTORS OF THE LITERARY FUND., 1823 May 12.; DS. 2 pp. #7254-b. Photostat.
    Bond, in T. J.'s hand.
  - THOMAS JEFFERSON, Monticello, to CLAUDIUS F. GOJON, Hyde Park., 1823 May 28.; ALS. 1 pp. File draft. Endorsed by T. J. RG-1/3/3.761.
    Opening of University uncertain, and appointment of professors delayed.
    [2003]
  - THOMAS JEFFERSON, Monticello, to [WILLIAM C. SOMERVILLE]., 1823 May 29.; ALS. 1 pp. #10028.
    T. J. thanks Somerville for a book on the French revolution.
  - THOMAS JEFFERSON, Monticello, to THOMAS COOPER, Columbia, S. C., 1823 May 30.; ALS. 2 pp. Endorsed by T. J. #38-750.
    Hopes Cooper will come to the University of Virginia despite revival of persecutions from the genus irritabile vatum. Columbian Register of May 10th contains no article by Ignatius Thompson but does have a message from the Governor of Connecticut.
    [2004]
  - THOMAS JEFFERSON, Monticello, to MARTHA JEFFERSON, Spring Grove, Lunenburg County., 1823 June 7.; ALS. 2 pp. File draft. Endorsed by T. J. Carr-Cary Papers, #1231.
    Advice concerning the settlement of George Jefferson's estate. His high regard for her father, George Jefferson, and brothers, George Jefferson and John Garland Jefferson. Mentions Patrick Gibson.
    [2005]
  - THOMAS JEFFERSON, Monticello, to WILLIAM B. GILES, Wigwam, near Genitobridge., 1823 June 9.; ALS. 1 pp. Photostat. Original owned by Herbert R. Strauss. #3508.
    Papers to T. J. Randolph at Richmond. Financial problems caused by recent death of friend. Hopes to open University in time for Giles's son to attend. Legislature to determine opening date. T. J.'s fractured arm.
    [3023-a]
  - THOMAS JEFFERSON, Monticello, to ARTHUR SPICER BROCKENBROUGH., 1823 June 16.; ALS. 1 pp. #2737-a.
    Sends drawings to correct ill effect of angles in passage of the Rotunda.
    [2006]
  - THOMAS JEFFERSON UNIVERSITY OF VIRGINIA. THE ROTUNDA. FIRST FLOOR PLAN., 1823 June 16.; Ink. Scale: 10' = 1". Paper CZ. 12 1/4 x 8 3/4 in. #171.
    Specifications on back. Construction began in 1823.
    [N-330, K-10, 171]
  - THOMAS JEFFERSON, Monticello, to ARTHUR SPICER BROCKENBROUGH., 1823 June 20.; AL. 1 pp. #2737-a.
    Letter of introduction for Mr. Miralla of South America, who is bringing papers from T. J.
    [2007]
  - JOSEPH CARRINGTON CABELL, Edgewood, to THOMAS JEFFERSON, Monticello., 1823 June 24.; ALS. 3 pp. Endorsed by T. J. #2791. Another copy: 3 pp. File draft. Endorsed by Cabell. Cabell Papers.
    Requesting T. J.'s advice on plan of jail for Nelson County.
    [2008]
  - THOMAS JEFFERSON, Monticello, to Messrs. JOHN WINN, WILLIAM C. RIVES, DANIEL M. RAILEY, JOHN M. RAILEY, JOHN ORMOND, HORACE BRAMHAM, AND GEORGE W. NICHOLAS., 1823 June 25.; L. 1 pp. Typescript copy. Original owned by Miss Jane Randolph Mcdonell. Printed: Ford-Bixby 276-277. #38-752.
    Age and debility prevent his attending Fourth of July celebration.
    [2009]
  - THOMAS JEFFERSON, Monticello, to JOSEPH CARRINGTON CABELL, Edgewood near Warminster., 1823 July 4.; ALS. 1 pp. McGregor Library, #5452.
    Plans for Cumberland jail. Literary Board to wait. Rotunda construction. Marble in transit New York to Richmond.
    [3025]
  - THOMAS JEFFERSON MEMORANDUM on CAPITALS for the UNIVERSITY., 1823 July 4.; AD. 1 pp. Endorsed by A. S. Brockenbrough. #2737-a.
    Thomas Appleton's account for the capitals; account of Jonathan Thompson, Collector of New York, for duty and freight; Thomas Bell's account for freight.
    [2010]
  - THOMAS JEFFERSON, Monticello, to SAMUEL J. HARRISON, Lynchburg., 1823 July 5.; ALS. 1 pp. #1774. Another MS. in MHi. Printed: Harrison 88.
    Forwards extract of a letter from George Ticknor of Harvard, complimenting the scholarship, zeal, and character of Harrison's son, Jesse Burton Harrison.
    [2011]
  - THOMAS JEFFERSON, Monticello, to ROBERT PATTERSON., 1823 July 8.; ALS. 4 pp. on 1 l. #15740.
    T. J. writes that he was contacted by "M. Jullien, a person of distinguished science" to be a contributor to Revue encyclopédique. The Revue's "object is, by correspondents established in every part of the world, to collect, as to a single focus, the discoveries, inventions, and advances of science generally in every country, and to present in a single mass those deemed worthy of being known." T. J. says that due to his age and "the crippled state of both my hands, writing is become too difficult and slow for me to undertake any correspondence." He hopes that by forwarding the matter to Patterson "some younger member of our society ... might be disposed to accept M. Jullien's correspondence." T. J. encloses Jullien's papers [not present] and closes by "renewing to the Philosophical Society the homage of my respect."
  - JOSEPH CARRINGTON CABELL, Edgewood, to THOMAS JEFFERSON, Monticello., 1823 July 18.; ALS. 2 pp. Endorsed by T. J. #2791.
    Thanking T. J. for his aid in planning the Nelson County jail. References to Mr. Crawford, Mr. Peck, and William Philips.
    [2012]
  - ARTHUR SPICER BROCKENBROUGH. MEMORANDUM on CAPITALS., 1823 July-August; AD. 1 pp. Endorsed by T. J. #2737-a.
    Cost of the capitals delivered at the University. Mentions Bernard Peyton, Thomas Appleton, Lyman Peck.
    [2013]
  - THOMAS J. O'FLAHERTY, Rumford Academy, to JAMES MONROE., 1823 August 3.; ALS. 3 pp. Endorsed by T. J. Greek, Latin, French, and English. RG-1/3/3.761.
    Application for position at the University of Virginia. Encloses letters from T. J., John Roane, and Thomas Cooper.
    [2014]
  - JOSEPH CARRINGTON CABELL, Edgewood, to THOMAS JEFFERSON, Monticello., 1823 August 6.; ALS. 5 pp. Endorsed by T. J. Enclosure: AD. 2 pp. #2791.
    Selection of the site of the Nelson County jail. Details of its plan. References to Arthur Brockenbrough, William Cosby, Mr. Crawford, Mr. Nelson, John Perry, William Phillips. Enclosure: memorandum of the contract made 29 July 1823 between Robert Rives, Joseph C. Cabell, and Thomas Massie, Jr., for the court of Nelson County, and William B. Phillips, who agrees to build the jail. Contract refers to Jefferson's plan.
    [2015]
  - JOHN ROANE, King William County, to JAMES MONROE, Washington., 1823 August 8.; ALS. 1 pp. RG-1/3/3.761.
    Recommends Thomas J. O'Flaherty for professorship at the University.
    [2016]
  - THOMAS JEFFERSON, Monticello, to ARTHUR SPICER BROCKENBROUGH., 1823 August 10.; ALS. 1 pp. Endorsed by T. J. RG-5/3.
    Change in his drawing of the library room of the Rotunda.
    [2017]
  - THOMAS JEFFERSON, Monticello, to ARTHUR SPICER BROCKENBROUGH., 1823 August 11.; ALS. 1 pp. RG-5/3.
    Door for the Rotunda.
    [2018]
  - ARTHUR SPICER BROCKENBROUGH, University, to THOMAS JEFFERSON, Monticello., 1823 August 11.; ALS. 1 pp. Endorsed by T. J. #38-174.
    Construction details regarding main door of Rotunda. Fire at the state penitentiary.
    [2019]
  - THOMAS JEFFERSON, Monticello, to GEORGE HAY., 1823 August 17.; ALS. 1 pp. #10464.
    T. J. comments on "Phocion's" article in the National Intelligencer regarding the dangers of the election of the president by states when there is no majority of electoral votes; mentions Col. Taylor's proposed amendment, the small chance of reform, and his own renunciation of politics.
  - THOMAS JEFFERSON, Monticello, to E. S. DAVIS, Abbeville, S. C., 1823 August 27.; AL. 1 pp. File draft. Endorsed by T. J. #38-174.
    Forwards plan of University with printed explanations. Reports progress of construction. Hopes legislature will enable University to open by liberating funds. University to be alma mater of South and West.
    [2020]
  - THOMAS JEFFERSON, Monticello, to [JAMES WESTHALL] FORD, at Mr. Dyer's, Charlottesville., [1823] September 1.; ANS. 1 pp. Endorsed, 1858 March 3, by T. J. Randolph. #6073.
    Ford to paint Mrs. Randolph's portrait at Monticello.
    [3025-a]
  - THOMAS JEFFERSON, Monticello, to ARTHUR SPICER BROCKENBROUGH, University., 1823 September 2.; ALS. 1 pp. RG-5/3.
    Terms of agreement with Giacomo Raggi for bases of columns. Mentions Mr. Negrin, John Neilson, and James Dinsmore.
    [2021]
  - JOHN WAYLES EPPES, [Mill Brook], to THOMAS JEFFERSON, [Monticello]., 1823 September 4 [date received].; ALS. 1 pp. Endorsed by T. J. Edgehill-Randolph Papers, #1397.
    Requesting payment of balance due him.
    [2022]
  - THOMAS JEFFERSON to [JAMES WESTHALL] FORD., [1823] September 8.; ANS. 1 pp. Endorsed, 1858 March 3, by T. J. Randolph. #6073.
    Ford to paint the President's (James Monroe's) portrait. Assistance in moving Ford's instruments.
    [3025-b]
  - JOHN W. GREEN, Culpeper, to DR. WATKINS., 1823 September 14.; ALS. 1 pp. Endorsed by T. J. #2737-a.
    Recommending Mr. and Mrs. John Gray as boarding-house keepers for the University.
    [2023]
  - THOMAS JEFFERSON, Monticello, to ARTHUR SPICER BROCKENBROUGH., [1823 September 17].; ALS. 1 pp. Endorsed by T. J. #2737-a.
    Recommending that Giacomo Raggi be given an advance, secured by alabaster and marble which he has permission to sell. Receipt for $50 signed by Raggi.
    [2024]
  - [ARTHUR SPICER BROCKENBROUGH] to THOMAS JEFFERSON, Monticello., 1823 September 20.; AL. 1 pp. RG-5/3. File draft. Endorsed by Brockenbrough.
    Arrival of Corinthian and Ionic capitals from Italy.
    [2025]
  - ARTHUR SPICER BROCKENBROUGH, University, to THOMAS JEFFERSON, Monticello., 1823 September 20.; ALS. 1 pp. Endorsed by T. J. #38-174.
    Arrival of Corinthian and Ionic capitals from Italy. Itemizes variations from directions given. Inferior to those done by Michael Raggi.
    [2026]
  - FRANK CARR, Red Hill, to THOMAS JEFFERSON., 1823 September 26.; ALS. 1 pp. Endorsed by T. J. Carr-Cary Papers, #1231.
    Sends three potato pumpkins and a cushaw squash with cultivation directions.
    [2027]
  - THOMAS JEFFERSON, Monticello, to WHOM IT MAY CONCERN., 1823 September 30.; ALS. 1 pp. Endorsed, 1858 March 3, by T. J. Randolph. #6073.
    Recommends James W. Ford as portrait painter. Mentions portrait of James Monroe.
    [3025-c]
  - ARTHUR SPICER BROCKENBROUGH. CONTRACT with GIACOMO RAGGI., 1823 September.; AD by T. J. 2 pp. Endorsed by T. J. RG-5/3.
    For carving of Corinthian bases for University of Virginia columns, to be executed by Raggi under the direction of Thomas Appleton.
    [2028]
  - THOMAS JEFFERSON, Monticello, to JAMES OLDHAM., 1823 October 7.; ALS. 1 pp. #7254-b. Photostat.
    Concerning work on the Rotunda.
  - THOMAS JEFFERSON, Monticello, to THOMAS APPLETON, Leghorn, Italy., 1823 October 8.; ALS. 2 pp. File draft. Endorsed by T. J. #38-174.
    Capitals received approved on the whole, but certain details unsatisfactory. Contract with Giacomo Raggi for Rotunda capitals. Requests price of bases for columns, wooden columns for interior, and marble squares for floor. Asks for engraving of Pantheon. Payment to be remitted by Bernard Peyton through Samuel Williams of London.
    [2029]
  - JOSEPH CARRINGTON CABELL, Edgewood, to THOMAS JEFFERSON, Monticello., 1823 October 27.; ALS. 1 pp. Endorsed by T. J. #2791. Partly printed: Cabell 282-283.
    Coffey's and Roscoe's books on prisons. Unable to find the Oxford and Cambridge Guide. New purchase of land will make it necessary to withdraw from the Senate.
    [2030]
  - THOMAS JEFFERSON, Monticello, to ARTHUR SPICER BROCKENBROUGH., 1823 November 2.; ALS. 1 pp. #38-174.
    Transfer of title of the University lands from the Proctor to the Rector and Visitors.
    [2031]
  - THOMAS JEFFERSON, Monticello, to JAMES PLEASANTS, GOVERNOR OF VIRGINIA, Richmond., 1823 November 12.; ALS. 1 pp. #3351.
    Literary Board funds inadequate. Bursar needs supplement for Proctor.
    [3026]
  - THOMAS JEFFERSON, Monticello, to JOSEPH CARRINGTON CABELL, Warminster., 1823 November 13.; ALS. 1 pp. Endorsed by T. J. #201. Printed: Cabell 283.